I'm a neuroscientist, and I study decision-making.
أنا عالمة أعصاب، وأقوم بدراسة صنع القرار.
I do experiments to test how different chemicals
أقوم بتجارب لاختبار مختلف المواد الكيميائية
in the brain influence the choices we make.
في دماغنا والتي تؤثر على قراراتنا التي نصنعها
I'm here to tell you the secret to successful decision-making:
أنا هنا لأخبركم سر صناعة القرارت الناجحة:
a cheese sandwich.
شطيرة الجبن.
That's right. According to scientists, a cheese sandwich
نعم هذا صحيح، بالنسبة للعلماء، شطيرة جبن
is the solution to all your tough decisions.
هي الحل لكافة قرارتنا الصعبة
How do I know? I'm the scientist who did the study.
كيف أعرف ذلك؟ أنا العالمة التي قمت بالدراسة
A few years ago, my colleagues and I were interested
قبل سنوات قليلة، كنا أنا وزملائي مهتمين
in how a brain chemical called serotonin
بكيفية مادة كيميائية في الدماغ تدعى سيروتونين
would influence people's decisions in social situations.
يمكن لها أن تؤثر على قرارات الناس في المواقف الاجتماعية
Specifically, we wanted to know how serotonin would affect
تحديداً، أردنا أن نعلم كيف لسيروتونين يمكن أن يؤثر
the way people react when they're treated unfairly.
على الطريقة التي يتصرف بها الناس حين يتم معاملتهم بطريقة غير عادلة
So we did an experiment.
لذلك قمنا بالتجربة
We manipulated people's serotonin levels by giving them
تلاعبنا في مستويات السيروتونين بإعطائهم
this really disgusting-tasting artificial lemon-flavored drink
شراب صناعي كريه الطعم بنكهة الليمون
that works by taking away the raw ingredient for serotonin
و الذي يقوم بعملية سحب المادة الرئيسية المكونة للسيروتونين
in the brain.
في الدماغ
This is the amino acid tryptophan.
وهو الحمض الاميني التربتوفان
So what we found was, when tryptophan was low,
و بالتالي وجدنا, انه عند انخفاض التربتوفان
people were more likely to take revenge
الناس يصبحون اكثر عرضه للأنتقام
when they're treated unfairly.
عندما يعاملون بشكل غير عادل
That's the study we did, and here are some of the headlines
هذه هي الدراسة التي اجريناها، و هذه بعض العناوين الرئيسية
that came out afterwards.
التي صدرت بعد ذلك
("A cheese sandwich is all you need for strong decision-making")
(شطيرة الجبن هي كل ما تحتاجه لإتخاذ القرار الصحيح)
("What a friend we have in cheeses")
( ان الجبنه هي صديقتنا)
("Eating Cheese and Meat May Boost Self-Control") At this point, you might be wondering, did I miss something?
(تناول الجبن و اللحم قد يعزز القدرة على التخكم في الذات) في هذه المرحلة ، قد تتسائلون ، هل فات علي شيء؟
("Official! Chocolate stops you being grumpy") Cheese? Chocolate? Where did that come from?
( رسمياً ! الشوكولاته تقلل من ثورات غضبكم)جبنة؟ شوكولاته؟ من اين اتى هذا الكلام؟
And I thought the same thing myself when these came out,
و انا ايضا فكرت بنفس الطريقة عندما ظهرت هذه العناوين
because our study had nothing to do with cheese or chocolate.
لان دراستنا لم يكن لها اي علاقة بالجبن او الشوكولاتة
We gave people this horrible-tasting drink
فقط اعطينا الناس هذا الشراب كريه الطعم
that affected their tryptophan levels.
و الذي اثر على مستوى التربتوفان لديهم
But it turns out that tryptophan also happens to be found
و لكن اتضح ان التربتوفان ايضا يتواجد
in cheese and chocolate.
في الجبن و الشوكولاتة
And of course when science says cheese and chocolate
و طبعا عندما يقول العلم ان الجبن و الشوكولاته
help you make better decisions, well, that's sure to grab people's attention.
يمكن ان تجعلنا نتخذ قرارات صائبة، اذاً سوف يستدعي هذا انتباه الناس
So there you have it:
اذا ها نحن ذا:
the evolution of a headline.
تطور عناوين الانباء
When this happened, a part of me thought, well,
عندما حدث هذا، جزء مني فكر، حسناً
what's the big deal?
اين المشكله؟
So the media oversimplified a few things, but in the end,
فقد قام الاعلام بتبسيط بعض الاشياء، و لكن في النهاية
it's just a news story.
فهو مجرد خبر.
And I think a lot of scientists have this attitude.
و اعتقد ان الكتير من العلماء يتصرفون بهذه الطريقة
But the problem is that this kind of thing happens all the time,
و لكن المشكلة ان هذا النوع من الاخبار يحدث كثيرا
and it affects not just the stories you read in the news
ويؤثر ليس فقط على الاخبار التي نقرأها في الصحف
but also the products you see on the shelves.
و لكن على منتجات نراها على رفوف المتاجر
When the headlines rolled, what happened was,
عندما انتشرت الاخبار، ما حدث كان كالتالي
the marketers came calling.
اتصل بنا مناديب التسويق ليسألوا
Would I be willing to provide a scientific endorsement
هل نحن على استعداد لاصدار تأييد علمي
of a mood-boosting bottled water?
لقارورة مياه تعدل المزاج؟
Or would I go on television to demonstrate,
او هل اوافق على ان اشرح في شاشات التلفزيون
in front of a live audience,
امام جمهور حي
that comfort foods really do make you feel better?
ان مأكولات الراحة فعلا تسبب الراحة النفسية؟
I think these folks meant well, but had I taken them up on their offers,
اظن ان هؤلاء يقصدون خيرا، و لكن ان كنت استجبت لمطالبهم،
I would have been going beyond the science,
لكنت قد تجاوزت هيبة العلم
and good scientists are careful not to do this.
و العالم الجيد يحرص على ان لا يفعل ذلك
But nevertheless, neuroscience is turning up more and more in marketing.
و لكن بغض النظر، اصبح علم الاعصاب يظهر كثيرا في الحملات الاعلانيه
Here's one example: Neuro drinks,
هذا مثال بسيط: مشروبات الاعصاب
a line of products, including Nuero Bliss here,
هذا نوع من المنتجات ، يتضمن منتج اسمه نيورو بليس " استرخاء الاعصاب"
which according to its label helps reduce stress,
و الذي طبقا لما يظهر في ديباجته انه يساعد في تخفيض التوتر
enhances mood, provides focused concentration,
يعدل المزاج ، يدعم التركيز
and promotes a positive outlook.
و يعزز النظرة الايجابية
I have to say, this sounds awesome. (Laughter)
اريد ان اقول ، يبدو هذا رائعاً. ( ضحك)
I could totally have used this 10 minutes ago.
كان بإمكاني تناول هذا المشروب قبل عشرة دقائق
So when this came up in my local shop, naturally I was
عندما ظهر هذا المشروب في المتجر المحلي، بالطبع
curious about some of the research backing these claims.
اصابني الفضول بالنسبة للابحاث التي دعمت هذه الإدعائات
So I went to the company's website looking to find
فتصفحت الموقع الالكتروني للشركة المصنّعة لأبحث عن
some controlled trials of their products.
التجارب العلمية لمنتجاتهم
But I didn't find any.
و لكني لم اجد ايأ منها
Trial or no trial, these claims are front and center
تجارب او بدون تجارب ، هذه الادعاءات كانت موضوعة بوضح
on their label right next to a picture of a brain.
على الديباجة بجانب صورة دماغ
And it turns out that pictures of brains have special properties.
و اتضح ان صورالدماغ الموضوعة هذه لها خصائص مميزة
A couple of researchers asked a few hundred people
قام عالمان بطلب مئات الاشخاص
to read a scientific article.
ان يقرأوا مقالاً علمياً
For half the people, the article included a brain image,
نصف عدد الناس كان مقالهم يحتوى على صورة دماغ
and for the other half, it was the same article
و النصف الاخر حصلوا على نفس المقال
but it didn't have a brain image.
و لكن بدون صورة الدماغ
At the end — you see where this is going —
في النهاية - تستطيعون ان تخمنو -
people were asked whether they agreed
قاموا بسؤال الناس ان كانو يوافقون
with the conclusions of the article.
على استنتاجات المقال
So this is how much people agree with the conclusions
هذا كان عدد الناس الذين يتفقون مع استنتاجات المقال
with no image.
بدون الصورة
And this is how much they agree with the same article
و هذا عدد الناس الذين وافقو على نفس الاستنتاجات لنفس المقال
that did include a brain image.
الذي يحتوي على صورة الدماغ
So the take-home message here is,
لذا ، النتيجة النهائية هي
do you want to sell it? Put a brain on it.
ان اردت ان تبيع سلعة ، ضع صورة دمغ عليها
Now let me pause here and take a moment to say that
دعوني اتوقف هنا دقيقه لاقول
neuroscience has advanced a lot in the last few decades,
ان علم الاعصاب قد تطور كثيرا في العقود القليلة الماضية
and we're constantly discovering amazing things
و نحن نكتشف اشياء كتيره بااستمرار
about the brain.
عن وظائف الدماغ
Like, just a couple of weeks ago, neuroscientists at MIT
مثل ، منذ اسبوعين مضت ، علماء الاعصاب في معهد ماساتشوسيس للتكنولوجيا
figured out how to break habits in rats
توصلو اي طريقة تغيير عادات الجرذان
just by controlling neural activity in a specific part of their brain.
عن طريق التحكم في نشاط الاعصاب في جزء من ادمغتهم
Really cool stuff.
هذه اشياء مثيرة حقاً
But the promise of neuroscience has led to some really
و لكن الحلم بمستقبل علم الاعصاب قاد الى
high expectations and some overblown, unproven claims.
توقعات عالية جدا ، و ادعاءات مضخمة و غير مثبتة
So what I'm going to do is show you how to spot
و ما سوف افعله هو ان اريكم كيف تعرفون
a couple of classic moves, dead giveaways, really,
في الحقيقه هي بضع الامثلة الواضحة جداً
for what's variously been called neuro-bunk,
وهي ما يعرف بمشروبات الاعصاب المختلفة نيورو بنك
neuro-bollocks, or, my personal favorite, neuro-flapdoodle.
نيورو بولاك ، و المفضل لدي ، نيورو فلابدودل
So the first unproven claim is that you can use brain scans
الادعاء الغير مثبت الاول كان : انه يمكن استخدام مسح المخ
to read people's thoughts and emotions.
لقراءة افكار و مشاعر الناس
Here's a study published by a team of researchers
هنا دراسة قام بعض الباحثون بنشرها
as an op-ed in The New York Times.
كمقال في صحيفة نيو يورك تايمز
The headline? "You Love Your iPhone. Literally."
العنوان الرئيسي؟ انت تحب جاهزك الاي فون . حقيقةً
It quickly became the most emailed article on the site.
اصبح هذا المقال الاكتر تداولا عبر البريد الالكتروني بصورة سريعة
So how'd they figure this out?
كيف قامو بهذا الاكتشاف؟
They put 16 people inside a brain scanner
لقد قامو بادخال 16 شخص في جهاز مسح الدماغ
and showed them videos of ringing iPhones.
و جهلوهم يشاهدو صور لاجهزة اي فون و هي ترن
The brain scans showed activation in a part of the brain
اظهر المسح نشاطاً في جزء من الدماغ
called the insula, a region they say
يسمى انسولا، منطقة يقول الباحثون
is linked to feelings of love and compassion.
انها مرتبطة بالحب والشغف
So they concluded that because they saw activation in the insula,
فوصلو لهذا الاستنتاج بناءً على نشاط في منطقة انسولا
this meant the subjects loved their iPhones.
هذا يعني ان هؤلاء الاشخاص يحبون الاي فون
Now there's just one problem with this line of reasoning,
هناك مشكلة واحدة متعلقة بهذا النوع من المنطق
and that's that the insula does a lot.
وهو ان انسولا تقوم بالكثير من الوظائف
Sure, it is involved in positive emotions
بالطبع هي مرتبطة بالمشاعر الايجابية
like love and compassion,
مثل الحب و الشغف
but it's also involved in tons of other processes,
و لكنها ايضا مرتبطة بالعديد من العمليات الاخرى
like memory, language, attention,
مثل الذاكره، اللغات، الانتباه
even anger, disgust and pain.
حتى الغضب ، الشعور بالقرف و الالم
So based on the same logic, I could equally conclude
لذا، بناءً على نفس المنطق، يمكنني ان اضيف بصورة مساويه
you hate your iPhone.
انك تكره الاي فون
The point here is, when you see activation in the insula,
الفكره هنا هي ، انك عندما ترى نشاطاً في منطقة انسولا
you can't just pick and choose your favorite explanation
فانك لا تستطيع ان تحزر و تختار تفسيرك المفضل
from off this list, and it's a really long list.
من هذه القائمة ، و هي قائما طويله جداً.
My colleagues Tal Yarkoni and Russ Poldrack
زملائي تال ياركوني و رس بولدراك
have shown that the insula pops up in almost a third
قد اثبتا ان انسولا تظهر تقريبا في ثلث
of all brain imaging studies that have ever been published.
الدراسات الخاصة بتصوير الدماغ التي نشرت على الاطلاق
So chances are really, really good
لذا، فان هناك فرصة جيدة جداً
that your insula is going off right now,
ان منطقة انسولا لديم مضيئة في هذه اللحظة بالذات.
but I won't kid myself
و لكن لن اخدع نفسي
to think this means you love me.
و اقول ان هذا يعني انك تحبني.
So speaking of love and the brain,
فبالحديث عن الحب و الدماغ
there's a researcher, known to some as Dr. Love,
هناك باحث يعرفه البعض باسم دكتور الحب
who claims that scientists have found the glue
و الذي يدعي ان العلماء قد وجدو الغراء
that holds society together,
الذي يحافظ على تماسك المجتمع
the source of love and prosperity.
مصدر الحب و الرخاء
This time it's not a cheese sandwich.
و هذه المره ليس شطيرة الجبن
No, it's a hormone called oxytocin.
لا، انه هرمون يسمى اوكسيتوسن
You've probably heard of it.
ربما قد سمعتم عنه.
So, Dr. Love bases his argument on studies showing
قام دكتور الحب هذا بالاستناد في جداله على دراسات توضح
that when you boost people's oxytocin,
انه عندما تزيد معدلات الاوكسيتوسن عند الناس
this increases their trust, empathy and cooperation.
فان هذا يزيد من ثقتهم ، تعاطفهم و تعاونهم.
So he's calling oxytocin "the moral molecule."
لهذا فهو يسمى الاوكسيتوسن ب" جزيء الاخلاق"
Now these studies are scientifically valid,
الان هذه الابحاث مثبتة علمياً،
and they've been replicated, but they're not the whole story.
و قام البعض بمحاكاتها ، و لكنها ليست كل القصة.
Other studies have shown that boosting oxytocin
فدراسات اخرى اثبتت ان تفعيل الاوكسيتوسن
increases envy. It increases gloating.
يزيد من الاحساس بالحسد ، و يزيد من الاحساس بالشماتة.
Oxytocin can bias people to favor their own group
الاوكسيتوسن يمكن ان يجعل الناس تنحاز و تفضل اشخاص من مجموعاتهم
at the expense of other groups.
على حساب اشخاص من مجموعات اخرى
And in some cases, oxytocin can even decrease cooperation.
و في بعض الحالات، الاكوسيتوسن يمكن ان يقلل التعاون.
So based on these studies, I could say oxytocin
و بالاستناد الى هذه الدراسات ن يمكنني ان اقول ان اوكسيتوسن
is an immoral molecule, and call myself Dr. Strangelove.
هو جزيء لا اخلاقي، و اسمي نفسي دكتور الحب الغريب
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So we've seen neuro-flapdoodle all over the headlines.
رأينا مشروب نيورو فلابدودل كثيرا في الاخبار
We see it in supermarkets, on book covers.
و رأيناه في السوبرماركت، في اغلفة الكتب
What about the clinic?
ماذا عن العيادات الطبية؟
SPECT imaging is a brain-scanning technology
تصوير SPECT هو نوع من انواع مسح و تصوير الدماغ
that uses a radioactive tracer
يستخدم اشعاع نشط
to track blood flow in the brain.
ليقتفي اثر سريان الدم في الدماغ
For the bargain price of a few thousand dollars,
و مقابل بضعة الاف دولار
there are clinics in the U.S. that will give you
هناك عيادات في الولايات المتحدة يممكنها ان تقدم لك
one of these SPECT scans and use the image
واحدة من هذه الصور و تستخدمها
to help diagnose your problems.
لتشخيص بعض المشاكل الصحية.
These scans, the clinics say, can help
هذه الصور، تقول العيادات، يمكن ان تساعد
prevent Alzheimer's disease,
في منع مرض الزهايمر
solve weight and addiction issues,
تحل مشاكل الوزن و الادمان
overcome marital conflicts,
تجاوز المشاكل الزوجية
and treat, of course, a variety of mental illnesses
و تعالج ، بالطبع ، العديد من الامراض النفسية
ranging from depression to anxiety to ADHD.
ابتداءً من الاكتئاب حتى القلق المرضي و اضطراب نقص اللانتباه و فرط النشاط
This sounds great. A lot of people agree.
يبدو هذا عظيماً، و الكثير من الناس يتفقون مع هذه الفكرة.
Some of these clinics are pulling in tens of millions
بعض هذه العيادات تجني عشرات الملايين
of dollars a year in business.
من الدولارات كل عام
There's just one problem.
هناك مشكلة واحدة
The broad consensus in neuroscience
هناك اجماع كبير في علم الاعصاب
is that we can't yet diagnose mental illness
على انه لا يمكننا حتى الان تشخيص الامراض العقلية
from a single brain scan.
من مجرد صورة مسح دماغي
But these clinics have treated
و لكن هذه العيادات قد قامت بعلاج
tens of thousands of patients to date,
العديد من الاف من المرضى حتى تاريخه
many of them children,
العديد منهم اطفال
and SPECT imaging involves a radioactive injection,
و صورة SPECT تتضمن حقن بالاشعة النشطة
so exposing people to radiation, potentially harmful.
بمعنى تعريض الناس لاشعاعات يحتمل ان تكون ضارة
I am more excited than most people, as a neuroscientist,
انا متحمسة اكثر من العديد من الناس ، بصفتي عالمة اعصاب
about the potential for neuroscience to treat mental illness
بخصوص امكانية علم الاعصاب العالية في علاج الامراض العقلية
and even maybe to make us better and smarter.
و ربما حتى ان يجعلنا افضل و اذكى
And if one day we can say that cheese and chocolate
و ان كان بإمكاننا في يوم ان نقول ان الجبن و الشوكولاته
help us make better decisions, count me in.
تساعدان في اتخاذ قرارات صائبة، فانا اول الموافقين
But we're not there yet.
و لكننا لم تصل هذه المرحلة بعد
We haven't found a "buy" button inside the brain,
لم نجد زر " شراء" في الدماغ بعد
we can't tell whether someone is lying or in love
لا نستطيع ان نعلم ان كان شخص ما يكذب ام واقع في الحب
just by looking at their brain scans,
بمجرد النظر الى صور مسح دماغه
and we can't turn sinners into saints with hormones.
لا يمكننا تحويل الخطاة الى صالحين بالهرمونات
Maybe someday we will, but until then,
ربما نستطيع في يوم ما ، و لكن حتى ذلك الحين،
we have to be careful that we don't let overblown claims
يجب ان نكون حذرين ان لا ندع هذه الادعاءات الضخمة
detract resources and attention away from the real science
ان تجرف الموارد و الانتباه من العلم الحقيقي
that's playing a much longer game.
و الذي يلعب دورا كبيرا و طويل المدى.
So here's where you come in.
و هنا يأتي دوركم
If someone tries to sell you something with a brain on it,
ان حاول شخص ان يبيعكم شيئاً به صورة دماغ
don't just take them at their word.
لاتصدقة لمجرد ما يقوله فقط
Ask the tough questions. Ask to see the evidence.
اسأل الاسئلة الصعبة، اسأل لترى الادلة و الاثباتات.
Ask for the part of the story that's not being told.
اسأل عن القصة التي لم تروى
The answers shouldn't be simple, because the brain isn't simple.
و الاجابة لا يجب ان تكون بسيطه ، لأن الدماغ ليس بهذه البساطة
But that's not stopping us from trying to figure it out anyway.
و لكن هذا لم يمنعنا من ان نحاول ان نفهمه في كل الاحوال
Thank you. (Applause)
شكرا (تصفيق)